Overview of the One Hundred Years of Revolutionary Internationals Conference proceedings 64025 64025
Hoover Institution Archives
One Hundred Years of Revolutionary Internationals Conference proceedings
1964
64025
Hoover Institution Archives
1 manuscript box, 10 phonotapes (1.4 linear feet)
Sound recordings and conference papers, relating to the history of Marxist doctrine and of the communist movement
One Hundred Years of Revolutionary Internationals Conference (1964: Hoover Institution).
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1964.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the library catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content of Collection
Sound recordings and conference papers, relating to the history of Marxist doctrine and of the communist movement
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution and Peace.; Communism.; Socialism.
- Sound recordings, 10 sound tape reels
  - Session 1, Monday morning, 05 October 1964 (Tape-cabinet Tape cabinet)
    Access
    Use copy reference number: 64025_a_0008862
    Scope and Contents note
    1. Introductory remarks by Dr. Campbell
    a. Dr. Sterling
    b. Dr. Campbell
    c. Dr. Claude Buss
    2. "The First International"
    a. Jacques Freymond, main speaker
    b. Boris Nicolaevsky, read by Barbara Burke
    c. Bertram Wolfe
    d. Dr. Missour?
    e. Bertram Wolfe
    f. Boyer, University of California
    g. Boris Nicolaevsky ?
    h. Stefan Possony
    i. Herminio Portellvila
    3. "The Second International"
    a. Gerhart Niemeyer, main speaker
    b. Carl Landauer
    c. Daniel Bell
    4. "The Anarchist Tradition"
    a. Max Nomad, main speaker
    b. Hans Gerth
    c. ?
    d. ?
    e. Richard Lowenthal
  - Session 2, Monday afternoon, 05 October 1964 (Tape-cabinet Tape cabinet)
    Use copy reference number: 64025_a_0008863
    Introduction - Drachkovitch
    Chairman - George
    1. "The Third International"
    a. Milorad Drachkovitch - main speaker
    b. Charles Malamuth
    c. Raymond Aron
    d. Herminio Portellvila
    e. ?
    f. ?
    g. ?
    2. "Comintern's Splinter Movements"
    a. Max Shachtman - main speaker
    b. Robert V. Daniels (University of Vermont)
  - Session 4, Tuesday morning, 06 October 1964 (Tape-cabinet Tape cabinet)
    Use copy reference number: 64025_a_0008867
    Berzinsky - Chairman
    Wolfe - 1st speaker
    Treadgold - commentator
    Hook - discussion
    Loewenthal - discussion
    Feuer - discussion
    Griffith (MIT) - discussion
    Wolfe - rebuttal
    Souvarine - 2nd speaker
    Shapiro - commentator
    Fainsod - 3rd speaker. Begins the discussion of Khrushchev.
    Triska - commentator
    Possony - discussion
    Bochensky - discussion
    Landauer - discussion
    Niemeyer - discussion
    Wolfe - discussion
    Fainsod - rebuttal
  - Session 5, Tuesday afternoon, 06 October 1964 (Tape-cabinet Tape cabinet)
    Use copy reference number: 64025_a_0008868
    Part 1 is not described.
    Part 2 includes a discussion of communism in Yugoslavia, as it relates to communism in the Soviet Union and China.
  - Session 7, Wednesday morning, 07 October 1964 (Tape-cabinet Tape cabinet)
    Use copy reference number: 64025_a_0008870
    Part 1:
    Sidney Hook examines the impact of Marxism on the Western world. Professor Foyer of the University of California-Berkeley examines Marx's concept of alienation. A general discussion follows.
    Following is a talk by a Swiss philosopher on Marxist thought in communist-controlled countries.
    Part 2 is not described.
  - Session 8, Gottfried Haberler luncheon lecture, 07 October 1964 (Tape-cabinet Tape cabinet)
    Use copy reference number: 64025_a_0008871
    An examination of Marx as an economist, not as a sociologist, etc.
  - Session 9, Wednesday afternoon, 07 October 1964 (Tape-cabinet Tape cabinet)
    Use copy reference number: 64025_a_0008873
    Part 1 is not described
    Part 2 is a discussion of Nikita Khrushchev and military rivalry between the USA and USSR. Following, a discussion of communist economics and ideology in general.
  - Speeches by Isaiah Berlin and Raymond Aron on the impact of Maxist ideas, 30 September 1964 (Tape-cabinet Tape cabinet)
    Use copy reference number: 64025_a_0008866
    Part 1 is an Isaiah Berlin speech: The Impact of Marxism in the 19th Century
    Berlin examines (a) the impact of the ideas of Karl Marx to 1914 and (b) the impact of these ideas on other thought movements. He says the two most important ideas are, first, monism and, second, the division of the world into children of light and children of darkness.
    Part 2 is a Raymond Aron speech: The Impact of Marxism in the 20th Century
  - Thursday panel, 08 October 1964 (Tape-cabinet Tape cabinet)
    Use copy reference number: 64025_a_0008861
    Several men discuss, as a panel and questions from the floor, international relations, war, cross-border broadcasting
- The remainder of the collection is undescribed.